# Ed Summers ehs@pobox.com / 240-478-7086 304 Brewster Court, Silver Spring, MD 20901

I am a software developer and data scientist with over two decades of experience designing, developing, maintaining and analyzing information infrastructures. I work best at the boundaries between the disciplines, and specialize in the application of both qualitative and quantitative methods to accelerate the work of research teams who work with the web as data.

## Experience

## Research Faculty

Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities

August 2014 - Present

- Social media data collection, analysis and preservation
- Digital humanities research and development
- Web and cloud based infrastructure development and sustainability
- Technical lead for Documenting the Now and Unlocking the Airwaves projects
- Instructor of record for courses in archival studies, digital curation, web and software development

## **Information Technology Specialist**

Library of Congress

March 2006 - August 2014

- Digital preservation and repository software design and development
- Lead Software Developer on the National Digital Newspaper Project
- Social Media Archiving (Twitter)
- Design and implementation of the Library of Congress Linked Data Service
- Standards work in the World Wide Web Consortium: SKOS, RDFa, eGov

#### Senior Software Engineer

Follett Corporation

May 2002 - March 2006

- Design and construction of a distributed knowledge management application
- Requirements gathering and project planning
- Web Service design and implementation
- Metadata harvesting and analysis

#### **Selected Publications**

Summers, E. (2020). Legibility Machines: Archival Appraisal and the Genealogies of Use. PhD Dissertation. University of Maryland. https://drum.lib.umd.edu/handle/1903/26731

Summers, E. (2020). Appraisal Talk in Web Archives. *Archivaria*, 89(Spring), 70-102. https://archivaria.ca/index.php/archivaria/article/view/13733

Summers, E. and Wickner, A. (2019). Archival Circulation on the Web: The Vine-Tweets Dataset. Cultural Analytics. Retrieved from https://culturalanalytics.org/article/11048

Proferes, N. and Summers, E. (2019). Algorithms and Agenda Setting in Wikileaks' #PodestaEmails Release. Information, Communication & Society, 22(11), 1630-1645. https://doi.org/10.1080/1369118X.2019.1626469

Summers, E. (2018). Appraisal Practices in Web Archives. SocArXiv Papers. Retrieved from https://osf.io/preprints/socarxiv/75mjp/

Summers, E. and Punzalan, R. (2017). Bots, Seeds and People: Web Archives as Infrastructure. *Proceedings of the 2017 ACM Conference on Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing, CSCW 17*. https://doi.org/10.1145/2998181.2998345

Brown, M., Ray, R., Summers, E. and Fraistat N. (2016). #SayHerName: a case study of intersectional social media activism. Ethnic and Racial Studies, 40(11), 1831-1846. https://doi.org/10.1080/01419870.2017.1334934

Steiner, T., van Hooland, S. and Summers, E. (2013). MJ no more: Using Concurrent Wikipedia Edit Spikes with Social Network Plausibility Checks for Breaking News Detection. International World Wide Web Conference. https://arxiv.org/abs/1303.4702

Baker, T., Bechhofer, S., Isaac, A., Miles, A. Schreiber, G. and Summers, E. (2013). Key Choices in the Design of Simple Knowledge Organization System (SKOS). Journal of Web Semantics, 20, 35-49. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.websem.2013.05.001

Isaac, I. and Summers, E. (2008). Simple Knowledge Organization System Primer. W3C Working Group Note, Retrieved from http://www.w3.org/TR/skos-primer/

Summers, E., Issac, A., Redding, C. and Krech, D. (2008). LCSH, SKOS and Linked Data. Proceedings of the International Conference on Dublin Core and Metadata Applications. https://dcpapers.dublincore.org/pubs/article/viewFile/916/912

#### Education

#### PhD Information Studies

University of Maryland 2015 - 2020

My dissertation project focused on appraisal practices in web archives and included a 16 month field study in the National Software Reference Library at the National Institute for Standards and Technology.

#### M.S. Library and Information Studies

Rutgers University 1995 - 1996

My studies focused on the use of the emerging Web to deploy metadata standards and services.

#### B.A. English

Rutgers University 1987 - 1991

In my senior seminars I focused on the study of the African American experience through the works of James Baldwin. I minored in Computer Science where I focused on object oriented programming languages.

References available upon request.